Nicholas Spyrison

Data Scientist

Summary

I am a published data scientist with more than 5 years of clean, analyzing, and visualizing semi-structured data. I have a passion for using data visualization to lead analysis, and abstract away the mental work allowing the audience to focus on the evidence on hand.

Skills

Focus Data visualization, dimension reduction, machine learning

Programs R, SQL, Python, Git, GitHub, Excel, VBA

Packages ggplot2, tidyverse, plotly, shiny, tidymodels, caret, keras, pandas, scikit-learn

Models Random forest, xgboost, neural networks, SVM, logistic regression, parameter tuning

Reporting Rmarkdown, Shiny, SSRS, Tableau, PowerBI

Education

2018 — 2022 Ph.D. Information Technology & Statistics,

under examination Monash University,

Clayton, VIC,

Dimension reduction, interactive and animated data visualization, machine learning

Thesis: Interactive and dynamic visualization of high-dimensional data.

- From 4 contemporary and 8 simulated datasets fit random forest models as baseline against
 SVM and XGboost
- Utilized SHAP and LIME local explanations to explore local linear variable importance to understand large residuals in the models
- o Created novel animated and interactive visuals to facilitate this exploration in a shiny application
- o Authored an R package hosted on CRAN to facilitate understanding and adoption

2008 — 2012 **B.Sc. Statistics**.

Iowa State University, minors in Physics and Mathematics,

Ames, IA.

Authored software (R Packages)

2022 **cheem**, Novel analysis and interactive visualization to understand the variable importance examining large residuals in machine learning models <u>Link</u>.

2019 **spinifex**, A ggplot2-like API for composing and exporting animated linear projections <u>Link</u>.

Experience

2018 — 2022 Data Fluency Instructor, Monash University,

Clayton, VIC.

- o R, python, Git, PowerBI, Rest API
- Data Fluency Instructor: Lead workshops (10-30p) on R, modeling, programming, PowerBI, & Git
- Teaching Assistant: Postgraduate data exploration & visualization | business & economic statistics.
- o Research Officer: census & text data; wrangling, analysis, & reporting

2016 — 2018 Business Intelligence Developer, CPI Card Group,

Denver, CO.

- o SQL, SSRS, Crystal, Oracle BICS, Excel
- Database reporting; across 4 reporting platforms and 4 database instances
- Developed supply chain report tracking a cost reduction of more than \$4M USD

2015 — 2016 Business Intelligence Developer, UDR Real Estate Investment Trust, Denver, CO. • SQL, SSRS, agile, SSAS/OLAP/MOLAP, WebFOCUS Responsible for transitioning reports from WebFOCUS to SSRS On-call for enterprise-wide ETL process 2014 — 2015 Business Intelligence Analyst, Heartland Financial USA, Dubuque, IA. o SQL, WebFOCUS financial reporting Dubuque, IA. 2013 — 2014 **Delivery Analyst**, *IBM* — *International Business Machines*, • R, Excel, VBA reporting to teams and management • Step-wise model selection with dozens of variables • ETL scripting via VBA macros for about 0.5 FTE savings across the team • IBM's lean/six sigma green belt, root cause analysis (RCA) 2010 — 2012 Laboratory Technician, The Ames Laboratory & Iowa State University, Ames, IA, Superconductivity & Magnetism Low-temperature Laboratory. o Conduct cryogenic material characterization, analysis, and publication 2010 — 2012 Physics Tutor, Iowa State University, Ames, IA. • Undergraduate classical physics to groups of 5 Awards and honors. 2022 Invited article for INFORM's OR/MS Tommorow 2022 RStudio: March "Top 40" New CRAN Packages Link 2022 Monash Postgraduate publication Award 2020 Melbourne Datathon 2020 – 1st place of several hundred entries Link o Changes to Victorian Intraday Electricity Demand Following COVID-19 Restrictions 2018 ACEMS Impact and Engagement Award

Publications

Doctoral thesis

2008 American Legion Award

2018 UseR2018 Datathon - 3rd place

2018 — 2022 Faculty Graduate Research Scholarship
 2018 — 2022 Co-funded Monash Graduate Scholarship

2011 & 2012 Nominated for Student Employee of the Year

[1] Nicholas S Spyrison. "Interactive and dynamic visualization of high-dimensional data". en. PhD thesis. Monash University, Mar. 2022. URL: https://github.com/nspyrison/thesis_ns/blob/master/docs/thesis_ns.pdf.

• Spatio-temporal animated visualization of over 7 million avian sightings

Journal articles

- [2] Nicholas Spyrison and Dianne Cook. "spinifex: an R Package for Creating a Manual Tour of Low-dimensional Projections of Multivariate Data". en. In: *The R Journal* 12.1 (2020), p. 243. ISSN: 2073-4859. DOI: 10.32614/RJ-2020-027. URL: https://journal.r-project.org/archive/2020/RJ-2020-027/index.html (visited on 10/16/2020).
- [3] Stuart Lee et al. "The state-of-the-art on tours for dynamic visualization of high-dimensional data". en. In: WIREs Computational Statistics (Dec. 2021), p. 21. ISSN: 1939-0068. DOI: 10.1002/wics.1573. URL: https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1002/wics.1573 (visited on 12/10/2021).

Software (R packages)

[4] Nicholas Spyrison and Dianne Cook. *spinifex: Manual Tours, Manual Control of Dynamic Projections of Numeric Multivariate Data.* 2021. URL: https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=spinifex.

[5] Nicholas Spyrison. cheem: Interactively Explore the Support of Local Explanations of a Model. 2022. URL: https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=cheem.

Conference proceedings

- [6] Nicholas S. Spyrison. "spinifex: visualizing local structure of higher dimensions". en. In: Brisbane, Australia, 2018. URL: https://user2018.r-project.org/poster/ (visited on 07/28/2020).
- [7] Madeleine Barrow, Jieyang Chong, and Nicholas Spyrison. "Changes to Victorian Intraday Electricity Demand Following COVID-19 Restrictions". en. In: *Melbourne Datathon 2020, Insights category.* Oct. 2020, p. 4. URL: https://github.com/nspyrison/melb_datathon2020/blob/master/_paper/paper.pdf (visited on 02/09/2022).
- [8] Nicholas Spyrison, Benjamin Lee, and Lonni Besançon. ""Is IEEE VIS *that* good?" On key factors in the initial assessment of manuscript and venue quality". In: *IEEE AltVis Workshop*. type: article. July 2021. DOI: 10.31219/osf.io/65wm7. URL: https://osf.io/65wm7/ (visited on 08/21/2021).
- [9] Nicholas Spyrison. "Animated Linear Projections". In: Summer 2022. INFORMS, May 2022.